Guide to the Margaret Taylor Smith Papers, 1918-2010 and undated, bulk 1980-2008 RL.01217
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margaret Taylor Smith papers
1918-2010 and undated bulk 1980-2008
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Margaret Taylor
RL.01217
19.85 Linear Feet
A native of Roanoke Rapids, North Carolina, Margaret Taylor Smith attended Duke University from 1943-1947. After graduating with a degree in sociology, Smith and her husband relocated to Birmingham, Michigan. Smith raised four children while taking an active part in her community through volunteer work and leadership. Smith's work as a research associate studying family life became the basis for a 1987 book, Mother, I Have Something to Tell You. Smith served as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations. In addition, Smith continues her commitment to Duke University by holding leadership positions on multiple boards, by acting as a founding member and chair of the Council on Women's Studies, and by enabling the creation of the Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund for women's leadership and the Margaret Taylor Smith Endowed Directorship for Women's Studies. The Margaret Taylor Smith Papers contain materials dating from 1918 to 2010, with the bulk dating between 1980 and 2008. The collection documents Smith's voluntarism, leadership, and philanthropic activities at Duke University, especially in women's studies; her sociological research on American families, specifically relationships between mothers and children, that resulted in the publication of a book, Mother I Have Something To Tell You; her social and family life; and her professional activities and voluntarism, particularly at the Kresge Foundation. The collection is organized into five series: Duke University, Mother, I Have Something To Tell You, Personal Papers, Professional Voluntarism, and Additions.
24,761 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, audio and video recordings in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
In addition, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Margaret Taylor Smith Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2008, 2010.
Biographical Note
A native of Roanoke Rapids, North Carolina, Margaret Taylor Smith attended Duke University from 1943-1947. After graduating with a degree in Sociology, Smith and her husband relocated to Birmingham, Michigan. Smith raised four children while taking an active part in her community through volunteer work and leadership. Smith was instrumental in founding the Legal Aid Society to provide legal assistance for low income citizens, and New Horizons, Inc. to provide service to individuals with disabilities. She held leadership roles in the Girl Scouts and the Junior League and participated in organizations designed to support children. Smith worked as a research associate at the Merrill-Palmer Institute of Wayne State University, studying family life and early childhood development. Her research became the basis for a 1987 book, Mother, I Have Something to Tell You. Smith served as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations. In addition, Smith continues her commitment to Duke University by holding leadership positions on multiple boards, by acting as a founding member and chair of the Council on Women's Studies, and by enabling the creation of the Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund for women's leadership and the Margaret Taylor Smith Endowed Directorship for Women's Studies.
Collection Overview
The Margaret Taylor Smith Papers contain materials dating from 1918 to 2010, with the bulk dating between 1980 and 2008. The collection documents Smith's voluntarism, leadership, and philanthropic activities at Duke University, especially in women's studies; her sociological research that resulted in the publication of a book; her social and family life; and her professional activities and voluntarism, particularly at the Kresge Foundation. Smith's original folder titles were retained. Smith, an avid note taker, often recorded information on the exterior of folders and manila envelopes. These folders were retained and appear in the collection. The collection is organized into five series: Duke University, Mother, I Have Something To Tell You, Personal Papers, Professional Voluntarism, and Additions.
The Duke University Series comprises materials related to Smith's leadership and professional voluntarism at the university, including correspondence, event planning notes, meeting minutes, endowment information, and speeches.
The Mother, I Have Something To Tell You Series documents the publication of the 1987 book, authored by Jo Brans, based on Smith's sociological research that describes how mothers deal with children who display untraditional behavior. Specifically, Smith researched American families whose children challenged social and sexual mores during the 1960s and 1970s. The series contains correspondence, drafts, speeches, and Smith's research related to the book, including the mothers' subject files, which typically contain written transcripts of Smith's interviews with the women, both with and without Smith's notes, questionnaires and sociological data, and audiocassette recordings of the interviews. Original audio recordings are closed to research. Use copies need to be created before contents can be accessed.
Materials related to Smith's social and family life are located in the Personal Papers Series, which primarily comprises correspondence with family, friends, and some professional associates, but also includes photographs, newspaper clippings, ephemera from Smith's days as an undergraduate at Duke University, and her father's World War I diary.
The Professional Voluntarism Series contains materials documenting Smith's professional activities, including awards, correspondence, speaking engagements, subject files, voluntarism, and philanthropy. The series particularly highlights Smith's work as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations; her volunteer work with the Junior League; and her interest in ethics and ethical dilemmas.
Later Additions have not been processed. Accession (2010-0066) contains email correspondence. Accession (2010-0135) includes addition research materials, correspondence, proposals, and other miscellaneous notes. Accession (2010-0164) includes correspondence regarding the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; the Duke University Women's Studies department; Smith's Class of 1947 and their reunions; and other miscellaneous materials and notes.
Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Photographs; Philanthropists -- North Carolina; Parenting -- United States; Mothers and sons; Mothers and daughters; Mothers -- United States -- Psychology; Diaries; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives; Voluntarism -- Women; Voluntarism -- United States; Women sociologists -- United States; Women -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Women's studies -- United States; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Kresge Foundation; Junior League of Birmingham, Michigan; Duke University. Women's Studies Program -- History; Duke University -- Faculty; O'Barr, Jean F.; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Brans, Jo; Smith, Margaret Taylor; Smith, Margaret Taylor
- Duke University Series, 1970-2008 and undated, 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  As a highly involved Duke undergraduate, Smith served as president of Woman's College student government while excelling in scholarship (Phi Beta Kappa), athletics (Delta Phi Rho Alpha), and in leadership (Phi Kappa Delta, White Duchy, Pi Beta Phi). After earning a degree in Sociology in 1947, Smith continued her commitment to the university through leadership, volunteering, and philanthropy. Smith served on the Executive Committee for Duke's Capital Campaign Fund drive, on the Board of Directors of the General Alumni Association, as a member and chair of Trinity College's Board of Visitors, and on the Board of Directors and Executive Committee of Duke's National Council. Particularly interested in women's issues, Smith was a founding member and chair of the Council on Women's Studies and served as president of the Women's Alumnae Association. Smith's generosity enabled the creation of the Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund for women's leadership and the Margaret Taylor Smith Endowed Directorship for Women's Studies. The series also documents the relationship between Smith and Jean O'Barr, who established the Women's Studies Program. Personal correspondence between the two women appears in the Personal Papers Series. The alphabetically arranged Duke University Series comprises materials related to Smith's leadership and professional voluntarism at the university, including correspondence, event planning notes, meeting minutes, endowment information, and speeches. Materials documenting Smith's experiences as an undergraduate at Duke and her social activities related to the university can be found in the Personal Papers Series.
  - Alumni Association Distinguished Alumni Award, 1996 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Awards, Duke Heritage Society and Half Century Club, 1991; 1998 (Box 1)
  - Board of Visitors capital campaign, 1990-2000 (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Council on Women's Studies, 1989-1992 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Dinner to honor Mary Grace Wilson, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Elly Elliott honorary degree, 2002 May 10 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of women's studies program, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Ford Motor Company and Women's Studies correspondence/outcomes, 1990-1991 (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Founder's Day, Duke University Chapel, 2001 October 4 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fundraising chapter and manuscript of Jean O'Barr, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Giving to Duke, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Gratitude for leadership of Council on Women's Studies, 1991 April 15 (Box 3)
  - Happer, Carolyn, Duke interview, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Hillsdale College inauguration, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Jenkins, Kimberly correspondence, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Kellogg grant, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Margaret Taylor Smith endowed directorship, 1996-1998 (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 3)
  - O'Barr honorary degree, Indiana University, 2002 May 4 (Box 4)
  - Sarah W. and George N. Taylor Endowment Fund, 1991-1995 (Box 4)
  - Trinity Board of Visitors, last meeting, 2000 April (Box 4)
  - Trinity Board of Visitors lists, 1988-1995 (Box 4)
  - What Makes Sense is That Things Don't Make Sense: Life's Continuing Dilemma, 1987 November 12 (Box 4)
  - Woman's College at Duke celebration, 2002 November 8-10 (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Women and Power, correspondence, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Women Imagine Change, 2000 May 4-5 (Box 4)
  - The Women's Center, 2004 (Box 4)
  - The Women's Center, Donna Lisker, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Women's health care, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Women's initiative correspondence, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Women's Studies, 1986-2008 (folders 1-6 of 9) (Box 5)
  - Women's Studies, 1986-2008 (folders 7-9 of 9) (Box 6)
  - Women's Studies, correspondence, brochures, and programs, 2001-2003 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Women's Studies Council leadership, 2002 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Women's Studies external review, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Women's Studies fundraising, 1990 (Box 7)
- Mother, I Have Something to Tell You Series, 1981-2007 and undated, 15 boxes
  In the early 1980s, Smith worked as a research associate at the Merrill-Palmer Institute of Wayne State University, studying family life and early childhood development. Smith collaborated with writer Jo Brans to publish the book Mother, I Have Something To Tell You in 1987. Based on interviews with mothers in Michigan, the book describes how parents deal with children who display untraditional behavior. Specifically, Smith researched families whose children challenged social and sexual mores during the 1960s and 1970s. The series contains correspondence, drafts, speeches, and Smith's sociological research related to the book, in addition to files on each mother, who appeared in the book under aliases provided by Brans. In keeping with the anonymity provided by the book, file names reflect aliases rather than real names. The mothers' subject files include written transcripts of Smith's interviews with the women, both with and without Smith's notes, questionnaires and sociological data, and audiocassette recordings of the interviews. Arrangement is alphabetical, followed by a large group of research files organized into rough book chapters by Smith.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Original audio recordings are closed to research. Use copies need to be created before contents can be accessed.
  - Articles in support of project, 1983-1985 (Box 7)
  - Author questionnaire, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Biographical data, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Book project notes, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - Book proposal, 1984 (Box 7)
  - Book proposal and Jo Brans notes, undated (Box 8)
  - Book tour and Doubleday correspondence, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Contract information, 1984-1987 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1987; 2007 (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Draft, Chapter 1, 1985 April 11 (Box 8)
  - Ego level assignments, 1983 (Box 8)
  - File from Jo Brans, 1984-1987 and undated (Box 8)
  - Focal child notes, undated (Box 8)
  - Forms and summaries, 1981-1983 (Box 9)
  - Initial correspondence with Jo Brans, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Letters to mothers and article, 1985-1986 (Box 9)
  - Margaret Taylor Smith story transcription, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Master list, 1986-1987 (Box 9)
  - My mothers, 1982 and undated (Box 9)
  - Packet for Jo, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Project idea development, undated (Box 9)
  - Project origins, 1981 and undated (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Publicity and correspondence, 1987-1997 (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Questionnaire for mother, undated (Box 9)
  - Rough draft, process, and outline, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
  - Rough drafts, thesis, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - Sentence completion tests, undated (Box 10)
  - Speaking engagements, 1987-1988 (Box 10)
  - Speaking engagements, Good Day Show videocassette, Boston, 1987 February 2 (Box 10)
  - Speaking engagements, WBZ radio show audiocassette, Boston, 1987 January 20 (Box 10)
  - Subject 10, Rosemary, 1981-1982 (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Subject 11, Janet, 1982 (folders 1-2 of 4) (Box 10)
  - Subject 11, Janet, 1982 (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 11)
  - Subject 12, Carolyn, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Subject 13, Betty, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Subject 14, Ruthanne, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Subject 15, Carol, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Subject 16, Lois, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Subject 17, Bonnie, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Subject 18, Dorothy, 1982-1983 (folders 1-2 of 4) (Box 12)
  - Subject 18, Dorothy, 1982-1983 (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 13)
  - Subject 19, Jean, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Subject 20, Kate, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Subject 21, Myra, 1982-1983; 1992 (folders 1-2 of 4) (Box 13)
  - Subject 21, Myra, 1982-1983; 1992 (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 14)
  - Subject 22, Rebecca, 1983 (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Subject 23, Suzanne, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Subject 24, Patricia, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Subject 25, Judy, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Subject 26, Marilyn, 1982 (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - Subject 27, Margot, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Subject 28, Susan, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Subject 29, Patty, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - Subject 30, Marian, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - Subject 31, Margaret, 1983 (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - Subject 32, Ann, 1982-1983 (folders 1-3 of 4) (Box 16)
  - Subject 32, Ann, 1982-1983 (folder 4 of 4) (Box 17)
  - Subject 33, Sharon, 1982 (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Subject 34, Ellen, 1983 (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Subject 35, Lucy, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Subject 36, Karen, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - Subject 37, Marie, 1982-1983 (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - Subject 38, Martha, 1983 (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - Subject 39, Elizabeth, 1983 (folders 1-3 of 4) (Box 18)
  - Subject 39, Elizabeth, 1983 (folder 4 of 4) (Box 19)
  - Subject 41, Gloria, 1983 (4 folders) (Box 19)
  - Subject 42, Joy, 1983 (4 folders) (Box 19)
  - Talk, with various dilemmas and several conclusions, undated (Box 19)
  - Thoughts on readings, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Worksheets used for editing, undated (Box 19)
  - Other materials (Box 20-21)
- Personal Papers Series, 1918-2008 and undated, 7 boxes
  Contains materials documenting Smith's social and family life, primarily through correspondence with family, friends, and some professional associates, but also through photographs, newspaper clippings, ephemera from Smith's days as an undergraduate at Duke University, and her father's World War I diary. Materials related to Smith's volunteer and philanthropic activities at Duke University are located in the Duke University Series. The Personal Papers Series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - 50th class reunion (Duke), 1997 Sept. (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - 60th high school reunion, Roanoke Rapids, 2003 Oct. (Box 22)
  - Clippings and notices, 1942-1946 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2000 July (7 folders) (Box 22)
    Arrangement note
    The correspondence folder for 1994-1998 contains an image of Jean O'Barr with Hilary Clinton.
  - Correspondence, 2000 July-2002 Dec. (7 folders) (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 2003 Jan.-2004 Sept. (7 folders) (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, 2004 Sept.-2006 July (7 folders) (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 2006 Aug.-2008 January (3 folders) (Box 26)
  - Clippings from Mary Lou Connolly's scrapbook, 1956-1966 and undated (Box 26)
  - Cramer, Laura house party, Hilton Head Island, 2004 Oct. (Box 26)
  - Cuba, Duke alumni trip, 2003 February (Box 26)
  - Duke clippings, 1940s (Box 26)
  - Duke correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 26)
  - Duke memories, 1940s (folders 1-2 of 4) (Box 26)
  - Duke memories, 1940s (folders 3-4 of 4) (Box 27)
  - Engagement and wedding, 1947 (Box 27)
  - Journal, 1994 Apr.-Aug. (Box 27)
  - Memories...Conversations with Sarah Waller Taylor and Bertie Waller Brown, 1981 Oct. (Box 27)
  - Mother, 1984-1985 (Box 27)
  - My friends, oral conversations, 50th reunion, 1992; 1997 (Box 27)
  - Photographs
    - Christening, 2003 (Box 27)
    - Digital prints, 2003 (Box 27)
    - Duke photographs, 1940s; 1960s (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 27)
    - Montreat, North Carolina and T. J.'s, 2003 May (Box 27)
    - My desk, undated (Box 27)
    - Pictures from refrigerator door, 2002-2003 (Box 27)
    - San Miguel, Roanoke Rapids, and Cape Hatteras, 2003 (Box 27)
    - Sicily, 2001 Oct.-Nov. (Box 27)
  - Picnic, Orchard Lake Country Club, 1984 June 3 (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Sid's 50th, 1999 (Box 28)
  - Taylor genealogy, undated (Box 28)
  - Taylor, Sergeant George N. diary, 1918 May-1919 Mar. (Box 28)
- Professional Voluntarism, 1962-2007 and undated, 5 boxes
  Series houses materials documenting Smith's professional activities, including awards, correspondence, speaking engagements, subject files, voluntarism, and philanthropy. The items give particular emphasis to Smith's work as the chair of the Board of Trustees of the Kresge Foundation, a national organization that awards grants to support non-profit organizations; her volunteer work with the Junior League; and her interest in ethics and ethical dilemmas. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  [Original recordings are closed to research. Use copies need to be created before contents can be accessed.]
  - Athena Award, 1998 Mar. (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Awards and memorial garden correspondence, 1996, 1999, 2007 (Box 28)
  - Correspondence and other writings, 1994-2008 (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Council of Michigan Foundations, 1992-1997 (Box 28)
  - Detroit Medical Center corporate responsibility, 1997-1999 (Box 29)
  - Detroit Medical Center, Hutzel Hospital, 1984-1997 (Box 29)
  - Dilemmas, 1986-1988 and undated (Box 29)
  - The Economic Impact of Women in Philanthropy, 1994 Oct. 20 (3 folders) (Box 29)
  - Ethics and dilemmas, 1987-1988 and undated (Box 29)
  - Gender equity reports, 1988-1994 (folders 1-3 of 4) (Box 29)
  - Gender equity reports, 1988-1994 (folder 4 of 4) (Box 30)
  - Health care talk, 1993 Feb. 12 (Box 30)
  - Heart of Gold Award, 1985-1987 (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Human development, 1986-1987 and undated (Box 30)
  - Human risk and solitude, 1987 and undated (Box 30)
  - Junior League Community Advisory Committee, 1998-2000 (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Junior League, 1987-1989 and undated (Box 30)
  - Junior League presidency, 1962-1964 (Box 30)
  - Kresge Foundation
    - Agendas and correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 30)
    - Annual reports, 1994-1998 (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Kresge Foundation (Box 31)
    - Correspondence and remarks, 1990-1995; 2005 (Box 31)
    - Council of Michigan Foundations, 1993-1997 (Box 31)
    - Crain's Detroit Business, Detroit's Most Influential Women, 1997-1998 (Box 31)
    - New Direction, undated (Box 31)
    - Retirement, 1997 June (Box 31)
    - Trustee-emeriti dinner, 1996 May 16 (Box 31)
  - Merrill-Palmer, 1974-1978; 1987 (Box 31)
  - Merrill-Palmer directories, 1978; 1980 (Box 31)
  - Panel - Class, gender, and race in the non-profit sector, 1996 Jan. 16 (Box 31)
  - Parenting and child care, 1986-1988 and undated (Box 31)
  - Philanthropy, 1998 (Box 31)
  - Quotes, 1986-1987 and undated (Box 31)
  - Remarks about the Kresge Foundation, P.E.O. meeting, 1997 Apr. 7 (Box 31)
  - Speaking engagements, 1986-1988 (Box 31)
  - Speeches and remarks, 1987-1988 and undated (Box 32)
  - Talks and information - Legal and ethical responsibilities of trustees and others, 1995-1996 (Box 32)
  - Volunteering, Junior League, 1971 and undated (Box 32)
  - Volunteerism, 1986-1990 (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Volunteerism and philanthropy, 1995-1996 (Box 32)
  - Wayne State University School of Medicine commencement luncheon, Distinguished Service Award, 1999 June 8 (Box 32)
  - Women of Achievement and Courage Award, 1999 (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Women and philanthropy, 1989-1996 (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Women working and volunteering, 1980-1983 (Box 32)
  - Women's Educational Equity Act study on gifted women, 1992 (Box 32)
  - Women's special connection and communication, 1987 and undated (Box 32)
- Accessions (2010-0066) and (2010-0135), 1981-1985, 2010, 1 box
  - Projects and correspondence, 1983-1985, 2010 (Box 33)
    Chiefly correspondence (Accession 2010-0135) from 1981-1985 regarding the Fox-Smith Project, conducted at Wayne State University, that studied the pain and stess of women associated with the non-traditional behavior of children. Also includes email correspondence (Accession 2010-0066) from 2010.
  - Letters to benefactors regarding the publication of research, 1985 (Box 33)
  - Proposal for book publisher, 1981-1982 (Box 33)
    Correspondence and outlines for proposed research and writing projects; outlines for steps of interviewing.
  - Research and correspondence, 1982-1983 (2 folders) (Box 33)
    Includes grant proposals, research proposals, correspondence, and notes on research.
  - Pat Johnson's research, 1983 (Box 33)